Guide to the Paul and Frieda Taylor Family Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Paul and Frieda Taylor Family Papers
1921-2015
1924-1950
RG 227
Yale University Divinity School Library
4
(9 boxes)
Correspondence, writings, and collected material document the life and work of educational missionaries Paul and Frieda Taylor and their family, who served at Huachung University in central China. From 1924 to 1927 Paul V. Taylor taught philosophy and English at Huping College, Yochow [now Yueyang], Hunan province. After a period in the U.S., Taylor served as professor and Dean of the School of Education and later Dean of the Faculty at Huachung University (Central China College) in Wuchang between 1929 and 1950. Frieda Taylor was a musician who taught at Huachung and was mother to the couple's three children; the family was often separated due to health reasons and political unrest.
Taylor, Paul Vivian
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jane Taylor Slabaugh, 2010, 2014
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Paul Vivian Taylor
1892 Sep 30 PVT was born in Reamstown, PA, son of Rev. and Mrs. Harry M. and Amelia Taylor
1914 B.A. from Muhlenberg College
1914-1917, 1927 Graduate student in Education at University of Pennsylvania
1914-1918 Taught Greek and Chemistry at Schuylkill Seminar (Albright College); met and married Frieda Fuehrer
1917 Ordained in the Evangelical Church, Allentown, PA
1918-1921 Taught mathematics at high schools in PA
1920s Pastor at Pennsylvania Evangelical and Reformed churches, including Lancaster
1924-1927 Sent to China a missionary of the Evangelical and Reformed Church. Taught philosophy and English at Huping College, Yochow, China
1929 Ph.D. from Hartford Seminary; Dissertation: "A Philosophy of Values in Christian Education"
1929-1950 Taught Philosophy of Education, Psychology at Huachung University (Central China College), Wuchang; Dean of School of Education (1929-1932), Dean of Faculty (1930-1950)
1936-1937 On furlough in the U.S.; family remained in U.S. when PVT returned to China.
1938-1944 Son Edouard, a graduate of Franklin and Marshall College, worked with his father at Huachung and taught at an Evangelical and Reformed mission school in Yuanling. Edouard spent 1945 working in India before returning to the U.S.
1938-1946 Due to war conditions in China, Huachung University moved to Kweilin, PVT led the college on its trek of 1500 miles and traveled to Hanoi and Burma for supplies. After furlough in the U.S. spent time in India and served as chaplain to U.S. forces and in relief work, before the University resumed operation in Wuchang in 1946.
1942 Doctor of Divinity degree received from Franklin and Marshall College, Lancaster, PA
1950 After spending six months in China following the Communist takeover, returned to the U.S.
1951-1962 Pastor at Zion Church, Frostburg, MD
1974 Died
Frieda Fuehrer Taylor
1895 FFT was born in Hazelton, PA
1917 Graduated from the music department of Schuykill Seminary, Reading, PA; met and married PVT
1924 Taylors left for China with their two young children, Eduoard and Jane
1927 Political unrest in China caused their return to Hartford, CT where PVT studied and their third child, Nancy, was born.
1929 Returned to China and headed the music department at Huachung University; performed in many concerts for the college and community.
1930s After their furlough, FFT remained in the U.S. due to the health of their daughter Nancy and war restrictions
1948 Returned to China; became seriously ill in 1949
1950 Returned to the U.S.
1957 Divorced from Paul V. Taylor and later married Ralph Alexander.
1967 Nov 25 Died in Wyncote, PA
Scope and Contents
This collection provides valuable documentation of the development and operations of Huachung University (Central China College) during a tumultuous time in China. Paul V. Taylor's work as Dean of the Faculty carried responsibility for the administration of internal affairs of the college, including the organization and direction of the curricula of its three schools, Arts, Science, and Education. According to a note left by Taylor, the curricula he worked out with Huachung President Francis C. M. Wei were adopted as standards for the whole of China.
Paul V. Taylor played an important role in the life of Huachung University. In 1922 it was proposed that a "Central China University" be organized, possibly located in Wuchang. The schools to be joined in this proposed university were the British Methodists' Wesley College in Wuchang, the London Missionary Society's Griffith John School in Hankow, the Reformed Church in America's Lakeside College in Yochow, the Yale-in-China, or Yali, institution in Changsha, and the American Episcopal Boone University in Wuchang. Due to conflicting opinions about an appropriate site for the union institution and a great deal of political unrest and upheaval in Central China, it was several years before a stable Central China (or Huachung) University actually came into being. Huachung operated from 1924 to 1927 but then was closed for two years because of student unrest and political events. In 1929, the school reconstituted itself on the western part of the Boone compound in Wuchang. During 1937 many people were moving through Wuhan, headed west in advance of the Japanese occupation. The school managed to complete the 1937 academic year, despite some bombings of Wuhan but by June 1938 it was evident that Huachung woul be forced to relocate. Equipment, books, and office records were packed up and shipped by river to Hengyang, and then by train and truck to Kweilin, where Huachung opened its academic year in September 1938. Kweilin was increasingly the target of Japanese bombing however, so Huachung had to move again, first to Kunming, and finally to Hsichow. Hsichow, a small country village twelve miles north of Tali on the Erh Hai Lake, was the home of the wealthy Yen and Tung families. A group of three temples outside the village became Huachung's campus from 1939 to 1946. When Huachung returned to Wuchang in 1946, it found many of its buildings in need of rehabilitation. Plans again were made to expand the campus and the decision of the American Episcopal Mission to erect a new plant for its Boone School outside the city meant that there would be more room on the original campus. Just as Huachung seemed to have cause for optimism, political upheaval hit again, with the Communist occupation of Wuhan in May 1949. The last Western faculty members left Huachung two years later, in June 1951. Additional records related to Huachung University can be found in YDSL Record Group No. 11, Archives of the United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia.
Most of the early family correspondence is from Frieda Taylor to her family in the U.S. From 1937, letters are primarily from Paul to Frieda, who remained in the U.S. after their furlough. The collection is of interest for the light it shines on the dynamics of missionary family life, especially under the disrupted political situation in China. Frieda was an accomplished musician and served as head of the music department at Huachang for a time, but was separated from her husband due to health and war conditions for many years.
Additional Paul and Frieda Taylor papers are available at the Philip Schaff Library of Lancaster Theological Seminary.
Some materials related to the Kuling American School and Kuling American School Association that were received with this collection have been transferred to the Kuling American School archives in YDSL Record Group No. 209. The Taylor children attended Kuling American School.
Arrangement
I. Correspondence, 1921-1999, n.d.
II. Writings and Notes, 1924-1960, n.d.
III. Biographical Documentation, 1922-1968
IV. Collected Material, 1924-1962, n.d.
V. Photographs
VI. Addendum, 2014
Missions -- China; Huazhong da xue, Wuchang, China
- Correspondence, 1921-1999; Series I
  - Family correspondence
    - Paul to Frieda; Frieda ("Fritz") to her family in the U.S. enroute to China, 1921, 1924 Sep (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Frieda to her family re. getting settled, Chinese lessons, 1924 Oct-Dec (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Frieda to her family, including re. daily life at Huping College, Yochow, 1925 Jan-Apr (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Frieda to her family, including re. student strike, travel to Kuling for summer, 1925 May-Nov (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Frieda to her family, including re. period in Nanking for language study, 1926 Jan-Jul (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Frieda to her family, including re. Kuling for summer, Yochow, 1926 Aug-Dec (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Frieda to her family, including re. period in Shanghai for safety, Nanking, 1927 Jan-Oct (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Frieda to her family, including re. period in Hartford where Paul was studying and return to Wuchang, 1929 Jan-Oct (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Frieda to her family from Wuchang, 1929 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Frieda to her family, including re. teaching piano in Wuchang, 1930 Jan-May (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Frieda to her family from Wuchang, Kuling, Shanghai, 1930 Jun-Dec (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Frieda to her family from Wuchang, 1931 Jan-Jun (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Frieda to her family from Kuling, 1931 Jul-Oct (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Frieda to her family, including re. life in Wuchang, children's illnesses, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Frieda to her family, including re. Ed and Jane at school in Kuling, Frieda and Nancy unwell, 1933 Feb-Jun (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Frieda to her family from Kuling and Wuchang, including re. piano concerts, 1933 Jul-Dec (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Frieda to her family from Wuchang and Kuling, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    - Frieda to her family, including re. teaching in Wuchang, children's activities, 1935 Jan-Apr (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Frieda to her family, from Kikungshan for summer, Wuchang; Nancy unwell, 1935 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Frieda to her family from Wuchang, including re. preparations for furlough, 1936 Jan-Mar (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Frieda to her family; Frieda and girls leave for U.S.; Paul to follow., 1936 Apr-Dec (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Frieda to her family from Lancaster, PA; Nancy hospitalized; Paul returns to China, Japan, 1937 Jan-Sep (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Paul to Frieda from Wuchang, including re. war situation, 1937 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Paul to Frieda from Wuchang, including re. air raids, 1938 Jan-Feb (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Paul to Frieda, Jane from Wuchang; including re. baby nursery in home, preparations to move college to Kweilin, 1938 Mar-Jun (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Paul to Frieda from Hong Kong, including re. Paul's illness while traveling, hospitalization, move of college to Kweilin, Edouard's return to China, 1938 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Paul to Frieda, including re. travel to Hanoi, transporting college to Hsichow, Kunming, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 29, 29A)
    - Paul to Frieda and daughters, including re. Edouard working at college, Paul and Edouard's trip to Burma for supplies, Edouard joining mission, 1940 Jan-Jun (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Paul to Frieda and daughters, Edouard to family, including re. Edouard's assignment to Yuanling, disagreement re. return of Frieda to China; Frieda denied passport, 1940 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Paul to Frieda re. trip to Burma for supplies, letters from Edouard; Paul starts for U.S. on furlough, 1941 Jan-Oct (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Edouard to family from Yuanling; Paul to Frieda; Edouard and Jane now married; Paul's ship enroute to China torpedoed and all belongings lost, diverted to New Zealand, India, 1943 Nov-1944 Jul (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Paul to family, Edouard to family; Paul waiting in India for documents and money, working in leper hospital; Ed and family move to India; Paul arrives in China in November, 1944 Aug-Nov (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Paul to family, Edouard to family; Paul becomes chaplain to U.S. forces; Edouard at mission in India, 1945 Jan-May (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Paul to family, Edouard and family to his mother and sisters; Paul continuing as chaplain based in Linchow, return to Wuchang, 1945 Jul-Dec (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Paul to family from Wuchang, 1946 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Paul to family from Wuchang; building house in anticipation of Frieda's return to China, 1947 Jan-Nov (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Paul and Frieda to family, H.M. Taylor to Jane; including re. Frieda's illness in May, her recovery, teaching music, 1949 Feb-Dec (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Various, including re. return of Paul and Frieda to U.S., marriage of Nancy, 1950 Jan-Dec (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Various, including re. separation of Paul and Frieda (1957), 1955-1972 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Circular letters
    - Newsletters written by Paul V. Taylor from Hua Chung College, Wuchang, Rangoon, 1937-1941 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Newsletter describing return from China, 1951 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - General correspondence
    - To/from Taylors
      - A-Bi, including to/from Arthur Allen, David Anderson, August Binder, 1940-1953 (Box 3, Folder 43)
      - Bl-Ca, including to/from Board of Economic Warfare, Board of International Missions of Evangelical and Reformed Church, to A. V. Casselman, Executive Secretary of Board of International Missions, 1937-1949 (Box 3, Folder 44)
      - Ch-F, including letter of Edouard Taylor to Rt. Rev. P.Y. Cheung re. establishment of Wei Tzo-Min Memorial Hall at Huachung University (1980), from John Coe, 1937-1980 (Box 3, Folder 45)
      - G-Ha, including from G. Gebhardt, Associate Secretary, International Board of Missions, from Ward and Lucile Hartman, 1943-1955 (Box 3, Folder 46)
      - Ho-K, including to/from Hsu, Kemp, Kimmel, Kwei, 1937-1954 (Box 3, Folder 47)
      - L-M, including to/from Leonard, Lyford, Miller, letter of sympathy to Frieda re. supposed death of Paul in 1944, 1943-1955 (Box 3, Folder 48)
      - From Cornelia Morgan, 1952-1954, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 49)
      - P-S, including to/from Logan H. Roots, 1942-1951 (Box 3, Folder 50)
      - T-Wh, including to/from Benjamin Tao, Francis C. M. Wei, Sterling W. Whitener, 1939-1960 (Box 3, Folder 51)
      - Wo-Z, first names only, including to/from Gertrude Zenk, 1937-1954 (Box 3, Folder 52)
      - Correspondence of Jane Taylor Slabaugh with United Church Board for World Ministries, and with members of Kuling American School Association, 1977,1986-1999 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    - Correspondence of others
      - A-C, including Allen, Beck, Brown, Constantine, 1939-1954 (Box 3, Folder 53)
      - G-W, including Francis C. M. Wei to Frank Price, 1940-1944 (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Writings and Notes, 1924-1960, n.d.; Series II
  Scope and Contents
  The writings and notes are primarily by Paul V. Taylor though not all are identified.
  - Lectures and notes re. China
    - Writings and notes for talks, including re. Christian education, birth of Chinese Republic, General Chiang Kai-shek, Nanking incident of 1927, 1927-1954, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Including Schneder Lecture, "Can Christianity Survive Under Communist Pressure in China?" (1951), "The Church's Post War Responsibility in China", re. Chinese religions, 1951, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Other lectures and sermons
    - Including "The Church and its Missionary Program", "Race Relations", "The Pastor's Role in the Ministry of Healing", "Corridor to Lent", 1951, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Including "Hosanna", "Pentecost", "Hitler's Germany", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Including "Some Thoughts About Christian Ministry, "All or Nothing", n.d. (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - Including Baccalaureate sermons, sermonettes, 1942-1960s (Box 3, Folder 60)
    - Radio sermons, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 61)
  - Essays and articles
    - Including "The Foreigner as a Messenger of Christ in China" in The Outlook of Missions, "In China Common Sense Prevails" in The Messenger, 1926-1943 (Box 4, Folder 62)
    - "China Missionary" - booklength memoir by PVT, 1940s (Box 4, Folder 63, 64)
    - Thesis: "What Shall We Teach?", 1924 (Box 4, Folder 65)
    - Travel stories, 1944, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 66)
    - Miscellaneous, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 67)
- Biographical Documentation, 1922-1968; Series III
  - Regarding Paul V. Taylor
    - Biographical sketch, citations re. chaplain work, honorary doctorate from Franklin and Marshall, 1942-1945, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Newspapers clippings and articles about PVT, 1922-1962 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Travel documentation, 1941-1955 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Church bulletins and programs featuring PVT, 1938-1943 (Box 5, Folder 71)
    - Chinese language lesson notes, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Regarding Frieda F. Taylor
    - Biographical information and concert programs, 1931-1968 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Regarding Taylor children
    - Certificates for Jane Taylor from Kuling American School and YMCA Swimming Test; silhouette of JT; article re. Rev. Edouard H. Taylor and program for his ordination, 1934, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 74)
- Collected Material, 1924-1962; Series IV
  - Regarding Huachung University
    - Central China College (Hua-chung) history, presidents' reports, minutes, 1930-1943 (Box 5, Folder 75)
    - Book: Huachung University by John L. Coe, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 76)
    - Correspondence re. college, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 77)
    - "Hua Chung College Weekly Bulletin", 1934 Feb-1939 Jan (Box 5, Folder 78)
  - Regarding missions
    - Re. Chen Teh Girls Jr. Middle School, 1937 (Box 5, Folder 79)
    - Articles, clippings about missions, 1943-1947 (Box 5, Folder 80)
    - Booklet re. Board of International Missions work, two issues of The Outlook of Missions that mention the Taylors, 1924, 1926, 1941 (Box 5, Folder 81)
    - Books: Who's Who in International Missions; It Happened in Hunan by A. V. Casselman, 1953 (Box 6, Folder 82)
    - "China Newsletter"; "China Bulletin", 1954-1956 (Box 6, Folder 83)
    - Foreign Missions Conference of North America General Recommendatinos concerning transportation, passports, 1942 Oct (Box 6, Folder 84)
  - China-related material
    - News articles, fold-out map of Shanghai, 1939, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 85)
    - Issues of People's China, China Monthly Review, 1951-1952 (Box 6, Folder 86)
    - Chinese-language lesson books, programs, etc. (Box 6, Folder 87-88)
    - The Linguist (1926); My Hall of Memory by Mary E. Myers, 1926, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 89)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Articles and booklets (Box 6, Folder 90-91)
    - Church bulletins and programs (Box 6, Folder 92)
- Photographs, Series V
  - Two albums of photographs documenting Taylors' initial voyage to China, 1924 (Box 6, Folder 93)
  - Loose photos including portraits of Paul Taylor, groups including Paul and Frieda Taylor, faculty of Huachung University, including Francis C. M. Wei, 1930s-1951 (Box 6, Folder 94)
- Addendum 2014, Series VI
  - Family correspondence
    - Paul Taylor to children while living in Frostburg, Maryland, 1965-1971 (Box 7, Folder 95-104)
    - To children while living in Corpus Christi, Texas during winter months and Frostburg, MD during summer, 1972-1975 (Box 7, Folder 105-111)
    - To children from Frostburg and after move to Uplands in Pleasant Hill, TN until sudden death in March 1976, 1975-1976 (Box 7, Folder 112-113)
  - General correspondence
    - Paul Taylor to/from others and regarding his death, 1957, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 114)
  - Writings
    - By Paul Taylor: including "Music and I", "Mt. Carmel Home", "A Midsummer Daydream", 1967, 1972 (Box 8, Folder 115-116)
    - By Frieda Taylor: "China Yesterday and Today", and an untitled account written upon return from China, 1926-1927 (Box 8, Folder 117)
  - Biographical information
    - Summaries of family biographies (Box 8, Folder 118)
    - Re. Paul Taylor: photos, honors, etc. (Box 8, Folder 119)
    - Re. Frieda Taylor: photo, recital program, etc. (Box 8, Folder 120)
  - Collected material
    - News clippings, church newspapers, booklets (Box 8, Folder 121)
    - Plan of Peking, Huachung University Alumni information, clippings re. China (Box 8, Folder 122)
    - Huachung University silk banner (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Photographs
    - Family photos from Nanking, 1926-1927 (Box 8, Folder 124)
    - Huachung University, Hankow flood of 1931, Boone Middle School, 1930s (Box 8, Folder 125)
    - Language School in Nanking, 1926-1927 (Box 8, Folder 126)
    - Yachow - people and scenery, ca. 1924 (Box 8, Folder 127)
- Addendum 2018, Series VII
  - Writings
    - "Early China Years: 1924-1942" by Rev. Dr. Paul V. Taylor, edited by John D. Snyder, 2015 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Photographs
    - Photograph album titled "Vacation Trip through the Yangtze Gorges, Summer 1933" (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - Photograph album documenting trip to Peking in 1934, Chinese individuals, missionaries, school buildings, athletic teams, etc., circa 1934 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Collected material
    - "Lushan Memories" - notebook of memories of Kuling American School compiled by Paul Sheretz, including contribution of Jane Taylor Slabaugh, 1988 (Box 9, Folder 4)